William Stanley Braithwaite Papers
William Stanley Braithwaite Papers
1916-1962
Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962.
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the African-American poet, author, critic. Correspondence, and manuscripts by Braithwaite and others. Notable correspondents include Arna Bontemps, Louis Bromfield, Sterling Brown, Marie Bullock, Witter Bynner, Cass Canfield, Bliss Carman, Bennet Cerf, Katherine Chapin, James Cozzens, Countee Cullen, Gustav Davidson, W.E.B. DuBois, Kimball Flaccus, Robert Frost, Claire and Nina Gerbaulet, Louis Ginsberg, Hermann Hagedorn, Leigh Hanes, Robert Hillyer, John Holmes, Langston Hughes, Georgia Johnson, MacKinlay Kantor, Joseph Joel Keith, Florence Lennon, Benjamin Mays, David McCord, Marianne Moore, Maurice Peloubet, Bliss Perry, Minerva Perry, Helen Channing Pollock, Ruby Altizer Roberts, Paul Robeson, Angelo Schmuller, Lulu Schultz, George S. Schuyler, Delmore Schwartz, Eli Siegel, Jules Siegel, Noble Sissle, Chard Powers Smith, Vladimir Sokoloff, Arthur Spingarn, Jesse Stuart, A.M. Sullivan, May Swenson, Ridgely Torrence, Carl Van Vechten, George Sylvester Viereck, Harold Vinal, Booker T. Washington, Robert C. Weaver, John Hall Wheelock, Margaret Widdemer, William Carlos Williams, and Roscoe Wright.
148861
Biographical History
William Stanley Braithwaite (1878-1962) was an African-American poet, literary critic, editor, and anthologist. Born in Boston, Massachusetts, he was for the most part educated at home, but his love of literature led him to his first job as an apprentice at the publishing firm of Ginn & Company. Over the course of his career he wrote numerous books of poetry and literary criticism, including Lyrics of Life and Love (1904), The House of Falling Leaves (1908), The Poetry of Thomas S. Jones Jr. (1910), The Story of the Great War (1919), Our Essayists and Critics of Today (1920), The Grecian Influence of John Myers O'Hara (1926), Frost on the Green Leaf (1928), and The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes (1950). Anthologies edited by Braithwaite include The Poetic Year for 1916 (1916), Golden Treasury of Magazine Verse (1918), The Book of Modern British Verse, Victory: Contributed by 38 American Poets, and Anthology of Massachusetts Poets (1922).
He served as literary editor of the Boston Evening Transcript, editor of The Poetry Journal in Boston, Massachusetts, executive editor for B. J. Brimmer Publishing Company, and editor of the annual Anthology of Magazine Verse and Year Book of American Poetry, published from 1913 to 1939. He was also Professor of Literature at Atlanta University for nearly ten years.
In 1918 Braithwaite received Honorary Masters degrees from Atlanta University and Talladega College, and the same year the NAACP awarded him its Spingarn Medal.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Stanley Braithwaite Papers is comprised of 3-1/2 boxes of literary correspondence and 3-1/2 boxes of manuscripts.
Correspondence contain more than a thousand letters, cards, telegrams and other items; correspondents include J. Donald Adams, Arna Bontemps, Witter Bynner, James Gould Cozzens, W.E.B. DuBois, Langston Hughes, Joseph Joel Keith, Paul Scott Mowrer, Helen Channing Pollock, A.M. Sullivan, and many others.
Manuscripts contains numerous manuscripts of the author's works, outlines for projected works, and typescripts of work of many leading poets collected for the Braithwaite's famous anthologies.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name. Manuscripts are arranged ???
Related Material
A large part of William Stanley Braithwaite's personal library is at Boston University.
Subject and Genre Headings
African Americans; Literature -- American Poetry; Adams, J. Donald (James Donald), 1891-1968.; Auslander, Joseph, 1897-1965.; Bardolph, Richard, 1915-2006.; Beebe, Lucius, 1902-1966.; Benét, Rosemary, 1900-1962.; Bligh, E. W.; Bonner, Amy.; Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973.; Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962.; Bromfield, Louis, 1896-1956.; Brown, Sterling A., 1901-1989.; Buchman, Marion.; Bullock, Marie, 1911-1986.; Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968.; Canfield, Cass, 1897-1986.; Carman, Bliss, 1861-1929.; Carpenter, Margaret.; Cerf, Bennett, 1898-1971.; Chapin, Katherine Garrison, 1890-1977.; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999.; Code, Grant Hyde.; Cozzens, James Gould, 1903-1978.; Cullen, Countee, 1903-1946.; Dargan, Olive Tilford, 1869-1968.; Davidson, Gustav, 1895-1971.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963.; Eaton, Charles Edward, 1916-2006.; Engle, Paul, 1908-1991.; Farber, Norma.; Fenton, Charles A.; Flaccus, Kimball, 1911-1972.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; Gerbaulet, Claire K.; Gerbaulet, Nina Joy.; Ginsberg, Louis, 1895-1976.; Gomme, George Laurence, 1853-1916.; Hagedorn, Hermann, 1882-1964.; Hanes, Leigh, 1893?-1967.; Hillyer, Robert, 1895-1961.; Holmes, John.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Johnson, Georgia Douglas, 1886-1966.; Kantor, MacKinlay, 1904-1977.; Keith, Joseph Joel.; Kline, Burton, 1877-1958.; Lennon, Florence Becker.; Mays, Benjamin E. (Benjamin Elijah), 1894-1984.; McCord, David Thompson Watson, 1897-1997.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Mowrer, Paul Scott, 1887-1971.; Peloubet, Maurice E.; Perkins, Maxwell E. (Maxwell Evarts), 1884-1947.; Perry, Bliss, 1860-1954.; Perry, Minerva.; Pollock, Helen, 1945-; Reid, Ira De Augustine, 1901-1968.; Roberts, Ruby Altizer.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976.; Schmuller, Angelo Aaron.; Schultz, Lulu Minerva.; Schuyler, George S. (George Samuel), 1895-1977.; Schwartz, Delmore, 1913-1966.; Siegel, Eli, 1902-1978.; Siegel, Jules.; Sissle, Noble, 1889-1975.; Smith, Chard Powers, 1894-1977.; Sokoloff, Vladimir, 1889-1962.; Spingarn, Arthur B.; Stuart, Jesse, 1906-1984.; Sullivan, A. M. (Aloysius Michael), 1896-1980.; Swenson, May.; Torrence, Ridgely, 1875-1950.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; Viereck, George Sylvester, 1884-1962.; Vinal, Harold, 1891-1965.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Weaver, Robert C. (Robert Clifton), 1907-1997.; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978.; Widdemer, Margaret.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963.; Wright, Roscoe.; African American poets.; African Americans -- Biography.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- African American authors.; American poetry -- 20th century.; American poetry -- African American authors.; Authors, American.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. William S. Braithwaite, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming literary correspondence
    - Aa-Az (Box 1)
    - Academy of American Poets, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Adams, J. Donald, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Auslander, Joseph, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Austin, Edmund O., 1950-1958 (Box 1)
    - Ba-Bz (Box 1)
    - Bardolph, Richard, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
    - Beebe, Lucius, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Benet, Rosemary, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Black, John, 1921-1948 (Box 1)
    - Bligh, E. W., 1919 (Box 1)
    - Bonner, Amy, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Bontemps, Arna, 1948-1960 (Box 1)
    - Brennan, John Payne, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Bromfield, Louis, undated (Box 1)
    - Brown, Sterling, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Buchman, Marion, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - Bullock, Marie, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
    - Bynner, Witter, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ca-Cz (Box 1)
    - Canfield, Cass, undated (Box 1)
    - Carman, Bliss, 1911 (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, Margaret, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Cerf, Bennet A., 1942 (Box 1)
    - Chapin, Katherine Garrison, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Clairmonte, Glenway and Joy (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Code, Grant H., 1939 (Box 1)
    - Coward-McCann, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
    - Cozzens, James Gould, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Crews, Caswell W., 1931 (Box 1)
    - Cullen, Ida and Countee, undated (Box 1)
    - Da-Dz (Box 1)
    - Dargan, Olive T., 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Davidson, Gustav, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - DuBois, W. E. B., 1939-1949 (Box 1)
    - Ea-Ez (Box 1)
    - Eaton, Charles Edward, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ebony Magazine, 1950-1956 (Box 1)
    - Engle, Paul, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Evans, Charles, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Fa-Fz (Box 1)
    - Farber, Norma, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Fenton, Charles, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Flaccus, Kimball, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Frost, Robert, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Ga-Gz (Box 1)
    - Gardiner, George L., 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ginsberg, Louis, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Gerbaulet, Joy and Claire, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    - Gomme, Laurence, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Ha-Hz (Box 2)
    - Hagedorn, Hermann, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Hanes, Leigh, 1951-1956 (Box 2)
    - Hillyer, Robert, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Holmes, John, 1956-1958; includes 2 copies of poems (Box 2)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1947-1959 (Box 2)
    - Hunting, H.B., 1938-1939 (Box 2)
    - Ja-Jz (Box 2)
    - Jackson, Ralph (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Georgia Douglas, undated (Box 2)
    - Ka-Kz (Box 2)
    - Kantor, Mackinlay, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
    - Keith, Joseph Joel, 1959-1960; includes 1 inscribed poem (Box 2)
    - Kline, Burton, 1955-1957 (Box 2)
    - La-Lz (Box 2)
    - Lawrence, Lillith, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Lennon, Florence Becker, undated (Box 2)
    - Ma-Mz (Box 2)
    - Mays, Benjamin, 1942 (Box 2)
    - McCord, David, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Moore, Marianne, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Mowrer, Paul Scott, 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Na-Nz (Box 2)
    - Negro Digest, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - Oa-Oz (Box 3)
    - Pa-Pz (Box 3)
    - Peloubet, Maurice, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
    - Perkins, Maxwell, 1939-1949 (Box 3)
    - Perry, Bliss, undated (Box 3)
    - Perry, Minerva, 1947 (Box 3)
    - Poetry Society of America (Box 3)
    - Pollock, Helen Channing, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Ra-Rz (Box 3)
    - Reid, Ira De A., 1941-1946 (Box 3)
    - Roberts, Ruby Altizer, 1956-1960 (Box 3)
    - Robeson, Paul, 1949 (Box 3)
    - Ross, David, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Sa-Sz (Box 3)
    - Schmuller, Aaron, 1959 (Box 3)
    - Schultz, Lula Minerva (Box 3)
    - Schuyler, George S., 1953-1958 (Box 3)
    - Schwartz, Delmore, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Scott, Dorothy L., 1942 (Box 3)
    - Siegel, Eli, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Siegel, Jules, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Sissle, Noble (Box 3)
    - Smith, Chard Powers, 1955-1961 (Box 3)
    - Sokoloff, Vladimir, undated (Box 3)
    - Spingarn, Arthur B., 1941-1955 (Box 3)
    - Stiles, Roberta, undated (Box 3)
    - Stuart, Jesse, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Sullivan, A. M., 1958-1960 (Box 3)
    - Swenson, May, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Ta-Tz (Box 3)
    - The Dryden Press, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Tillman, N. P., 1944-1948 (Box 3)
    - Torrence, Ridgeley, 1942; inscribed photo (Box 3)
    - Tutin, William L., 1945-1947 (Box 3)
    - Ua-Uz (Box 3)
    - Va-Vz (Box 3)
    - Van Vechten, Carl, 1947 (Box 3)
    - Viereck, George Sylvester, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Vinal, Howard, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Wa-Wz (Box 3)
    - Wakefield, Oliver Lindsay (Box 3)
    - Washington, Booker T., 1939 (Box 3)
    - Weaver, Robert C., 1961 (Box 3)
    - Wheelock, John Hall, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Whitcomb, George Faunce, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Widdemer, Margaret, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Williams, William Carlos, undated (Box 3)
    - Wright, Roscoe, 1927-1962 (Box 3)
    - Unidentifiable correspondence signed "Barbara" (Box 3)
    - Unidentifiable correspondence (Box 3)
    - Incoming family correspondence (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
  - Outgoing literary correspondence
    - Aa-Bz (Box 4)
    - Ca-Gz (Box 4)
    - Ha-Lz (Box 4)
    - Ma-Pz (Box 4)
    - Qa-Zz (Box 4)
    - Unidentifiable and/or fragments (Box 4)
- Manuscripts
  - Verse by others
    - Aa-Cz, typescripts (Box 4)
    - Da-Lz, typescripts (Box 4)
    - Hanes, Leigh, holograph, with short article (Box 4)
    - Ma-Rz, typescripts (Box 4)
    - Sa-Zz, typescripts (Box 4)
    - Printed copies of verse by others (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous typescript copies of poems by other (Box 4)
  - Verse by Braithwaite
    - Holograph (Box 5)
      A Christmas card you cannot read
      Among my friends and those
      An Easter Song For Wynone
      A Mother's Prayer
      A rose to the living is more
      Dear Ike, we honor and adore you
      For Marianne Moore
      Go, book, to her be heart and eyes
      Idiomatic
      If Herrick had his Julia
      I looked at the moon
      In a sunken Pool
      Not Wise Enough
      Of One Who Spurns the Lyric
      One Book Review by J—
      On An Alabaster Burial Urn
      Return of the Native
      Rorty
      Stardust Vendor
      Shadows
      Tenderer I Would Be
      The Greeks Lost the Word For It
      The Lady And the Census Taker
      The Praying Hands
      There are windows to houses
      This is the year of great decision
      Though he may come but once a year
      Three tall candles may they flame
      To Helen Channing Pollock
      To Jane and Julie
      To Laurie My Granddaughter On Her Second Birthday
      To M.
      To Robert Frost
      We are the music-makers
      What can I wish you more than this
      When Mary, flower of maiden head
      Who Makes the Wind
    - Typescript (Box 5)
      Ascension
      Ambrose Bierce
      Anne Bradstreet and Phyllis Wheatley
      An Easter Song
      Another
      Avowal
      Bewitchment
      Blessing
      Bryant Park
      Chastisement
      Christopher Cinicampius Writes a Letter in Memory of his Friend Erasmus
      Del Cascar
      Cynthia Taggart
      Emily Bronte
      Ever Old, Ever New
      Femininity
      Flower of the Hawthorne
      For a Lady Who Asked Me to Write a Petrarchan Sonnet
      For Truda T. Weil
      Guynemer
      If I Were Prickled With the Scratch of Rhyme
      Iron and corn to rust and ripen
      How Have I Reached This Height That Now Surveys
      Life's Trivia
      Loves of the Puppets
      Mr. Kasebier's Orchard
      Mysteries
      Keat's Birthday
      Of Dead Ladies
      O Lady of the Hawthorne
      On Being Threatened With Blindness
      On the Centenary of the Birth of Booker T. Washington
      Only To the Soul Is lt Given
      On the Jiffy Bag
      Petition
      Photograph of Robert Frost
      Prophecy
      Remembrance of Elizabethan Springtide
      Saint Rose of Lima
      Sara Teasdale
      Sea Honeymoon To Icaria
      Sidney Lanier
      Should the bright world now fade out on a weight
      Signal
      Some Literary Epigrams
      Tender I Would Be
      The Age of Ebony
      The Echo of the Singers
      The Ghost In the Carpet
      The Greeks Lost the Word For lt
      The Hour Most Still
      The King's Daughter
      The Mutuel Player's Prayer
      These things now swept me on a tide
      The Palm
      The Septuagenarian Approaches Christmas
      The Signal
      The Tragedy of Lovers Leap
      They Are Awakened
      Time For A Change
      To Jane And Julie
      To Marianne Moore For Her Birthday
      To One In Whose Feeding Lurks A Dragon
      To Robert Herrick, In the Spring
      To Smith, — Her Dog
      Trail-Breaker
      With a fierce spring and loud alarm
      Wreckage
      Will There Be Another April
      You Flashed Like A Cardinal Bird
  - Articles and books by Braithwaite
    - Selected Poems, typescript (Box 5)
    - Selected Poems, printer's proofs (Box 5)
    - A Letter In Memory of Erasmus and Other Poems, typescript (Box 5)
    - Anthology of Magazine Verse and Yearbook of American Poetry 1958, partial proofs (Box 5)
    - The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes, typescript table of contents (Box 5)
    - The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes, typescript copies, Chapters I, II, III, V, VII, XVI, XVII, XVIII, XIX, XX, XX (Box 5)
    - The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes, typescript copies, Chapters XXII, XXIV, XXV, XXVI, XXVII, XXVIII, XXIX, XXX, XXXI, XXXII (Box 5)
    - The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes., typescript partial manuscript (Box 5)
    - unnumbered chapters on Emily, Charlotte, Branwell Bronte, Emily's Poems, and The Bronte Family., typescript copies (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous material on The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes. (Box 5)
    - Proposed book A Century of the Negro Novelist, holograph outline (Box 6)
    - Proposed book A Century of the Negro Novelist, holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Proposed book A Century of the Negro Novelist, typescript copies (Box 6)
    - Further material concerning author's proposal for book A Century of the Negro Novelist (Box 6)
    - Article, "Alain Locke and Negro Authorship", typescript copies (Box 6)
    - Article, A Pioneer Magazine, typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "A Prophetic Bible Course", holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Article, "A Prophetic Bible Course", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "Dispensational Truth or God's Plan and Purpose In The Ages", holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Article, "Dispensational Truth or God's Plan and Purpose In The Ages", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "Emily Bronte: A Study in Literary Alchemy.", holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Article, "Emily Bronte: A Study in Literary Alchemy.", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "Gallant Sir Harry Vane.", typescript (Box 6)
    - Pandora's Garden: An Anthology of the Women Poets of America, typescript outline (Box 6)
    - Story of the Years Between: 1918-1939, typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "The Contemporary Novelist.", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "The Feast of the Poets.", typescript (Box 6)
    - The House Under Arcturus: An Autobiography, typescript partial manuscript (Box 6)
    - Article, "The Magazines and The Poets and Other Studies in Prose and Verse.", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "The Negro in American Literature.", typescript (Box 6)
    - Article, "The New Emancipation.", typescript (Box 6)
    - The Years Between 1918-1939, typescript table of contents (Box 6)
    - The Years Between 1918-1939, holograph copy (Box 6)
    - The Years Between 1918-1939, transcript fragments (Box 6)
    - Article, "Three Friends: A Sheaf of Memoirs", holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Article on Boston and New England, typescript (Box 6)
    - Article on W. E. B. DuBois, holograph copy (Box 6)
    - Article on Negro Community of New York, typescript (Box 6)
    - Typescript and holograph copies of several short manuscripts (Box 6)
    - Several short articles, holograph copies (Box 6)
    - Several short articles, typescript copies (Box 6)
  - Reviews
    - Reviews by W. S. Braithwaite, holograph copies (Box 6)
    - Reviews by W. S. Braithwaite, typescript copies (Box 6)
    - Reviews, printed copies (Box 6)
    - Review of The Bewitched Parsonage: The Story of the Brontes (Box 6)
    - Reviews of Anthology of Magazine Verse and Yearbook of American Poetry (Box 6)
    - Review of Selected Poems (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous reviews (Box 6)
  - Other material
    - General clippings (Box 6)
    - Material concerning anthology (Box 6)
    - Song with lyrics by W. S. Braithwaite (Box 6)
    - Photograph of W. S. Braithwaite (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 6)
    - Typescript articles on W. S. Braithwaite (Box 6)
    - Tape recording: "Enjoyment of Poetry" series, WEVD, 6 Jul 1958 (Box 7)
    - Pamphlets and programs (Box 7)
    - Magazines, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 7)